<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Funcdata | Technoskald]]></title>
  <link href="http://technoskald.github.io/blog/categories/funcdata/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://technoskald.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-25T13:50:23-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://technoskald.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kyle Maxwell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project Euler: Problem 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://technoskald.github.io/blog/2013/12/25/project-euler-problem-1/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-25T13:28:12-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://technoskald.github.io/blog/2013/12/25/project-euler-problem-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>NB: This is a repost of something I wrote on an old blog. Original post <a href="http://funcdata.wordpress.com/2012/05/11/project-euler-problem-1/">here</a>. Minor edits / additions to update for this newer context.</em></p>

<h2>Find the sum of all the multiples of 3 or 5 below 1000.</h2>

<p>My <a href="https://github.com/technoskald/projecteuler/blob/master/prob1.py">original solution</a> for this problem, like almost all the others, uses old-school imperative programming that we can do in almost any language.</p>

<p>``` python Project Euler Problem 1 the Easy Way
n=0
for i in range(1000):</p>

<pre><code>if ((i % 3) == 0) or ((i % 5) == 0):
    n += i
</code></pre>

<p>print n
```</p>

<p>More to the point, we can also <a href="https://github.com/technoskald/funcdata/blob/master/projecteuler/p001.py">do this</a> in idiomatic Python:</p>

<p><code>python Project Euler Problem 1 the Pythonic Way
print sum(i for i in range(1,1000) if i%3==0 or i%5==0)
</code></p>

<p>Both give the correct answer<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, but we used an <a href="http://docs.python.org/glossary.html#term-iterable">iterable</a> (sequence) in the second case to do the same thing as the <code>for</code> loop in the first example. We also don&rsquo;t need to maintain our own summation variable like <code>n</code>. Because of the small range of numbers we need to consider<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, I couldn&rsquo;t find any significant difference in the average run times of these two programs. And I&rsquo;ve wanted to explore <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Functional_programming">functional programming</a>, too.</p>

<p><code>python Project Euler Problem 1 the Functional Way
print sum(list(set(range(0,1000,3) + range(0,1000,5))))
</code></p>

<p>This avoids maintaining <em>any</em> internal state like we did with the <code>i</code> variable above. For purposes of functional programming, I think that this would have been the optimal solution.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I won&rsquo;t list the actual problem answers here. I know somebody can just copy and paste the code, but printing the actual answer as opposed to explaining how to solve it feels too much like cheating.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>In some later problems, I&rsquo;ll just get any needed parameters from the command line to facilitate testing and debugging.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
