<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Meta | Technoskald]]></title>
  <link href="http://technoskald.github.io/blog/categories/meta/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://technoskald.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-29T23:04:54-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://technoskald.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kyle Maxwell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2014 Tech goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://technoskald.github.io/blog/2013/12/29/2014-tech-goals/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-29T14:37:38-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://technoskald.github.io/blog/2013/12/29/2014-tech-goals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While the calendar will flip in a few days, I&rsquo;ve had some time off and and naturally have spent some time thinking about the future. What do I want to learn and improve in my technical skills over the next year or so? Most of the following can be summed up in two &ldquo;meta goals&rdquo;: <strong>write more code</strong> and <strong>get back to math and computer science.</strong></p>

<p>At the moment, I plan to work primarily in Python and C,  although that could change depending on projects and other similar factors. Today, I write most of my <a href="http://osrc.dfm.io/technoskald">open source code</a> in Python, and my closed source code for work leans even more heavily in that direction. C was my first love, though, and I still use a subset of it when working with Arduino. Other languages might crop up for specific projects, I suppose.</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Submit a solid proposal to speak at DEFCON.</strong> I have no direct control over the acceptance of my proposal, but I can make sure that I work on something cool and submit a proposal that&rsquo;s worthy of serious consideration. Almost certainly this will deal with OSINT or network forensics.</li>
<li><strong>Complete the <a href="http://www.matasano.com/articles/crypto-challenges/">Matasano Crypto Challenges</a></strong> This will help me achieve a good hacker-level understanding of cryptography. Recent news events provide part of the motivation to learn a lot more about all this.</li>
<li><strong>Complete at least 100 problems from <a href="http://projecteuler.net">Project Euler</a>, including writeups.</strong> This project scratches a number of different itches for me, all in good ways.</li>
<li><strong>Build at least one really cool hardware project.</strong> I have a recent interest in hardware hacking, mostly around the so-called &ldquo;Internet of Things&rdquo;, and so (likely in conjunction with my daughter) I want to build something cool, albeit undetermined right now.</li>
</ol>


<p>For clarity&rsquo;s sake, of course I have other things I want to accomplish during the next few months to a year. Some of them almost fit here (more educational advocacy and volunteerism) and some don&rsquo;t (personal and family goals). But the above looks to me like a solid set of things to work on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
